Hi everyone! This is Professor Bassem Allam. I am a marine biologist at Stony Brook University, and
I study shellfish physiology and health! As part of my job, I am in charge of monitoring the health
of shellfish species in New York State waters. So today, I am on a fishing boat in
Long Island Sound, and I am collecting oysters for our lab. Let's go back to the campus!
Welcome to the lab! In this session, you will get familiar with oyster
external and internal anatomy, and you will receive a hands-on experience of some of the diagnostic
tools we use to identify pests and parasites affecting these animals!
While I will be dissecting, my colleague Nora will be narrating the procedure.
Let's start with some tools you will be using during this procedure
A syringe and needle, a clam shucking knife, scissors, tweezers, and a scalpel.
This is the eastern oyster, Crassostrea virginica
One of the most important species of bivalve along the coast of the US,
including New York State
As you can see, the two shells are not identical. While the bottom or "left"
shell of the oyster is curved,
the top or "right" shell is flat.
The oyster has a narrow hinged end, and a wide fluted end. The hinge is the area
where the two shells are connected.
The right side of the right shell is called the interior end, while the left side
is called the posterior end.
The mouth is located at the interior end of the animal, while the rectum is located at the
posterior end.
Looking at the shell, it is possible to see artifacts, including worm tubes attached to the shell.
The tubes may contain polychaete worms such as Polydorus species.
In addition, it is not rare to observe small holes left by sponges that colonized the shell.
To open or "shuck" the oyster, we will be using the hinge entering shucking method.
Let's first act what to do:
Position the oyster cupped side down, with the hinge facing you.
Insert the tip of the oyster knife between the two shells, where they are joined at the hinge.
The curved tip must be oriented to the top.
Move the blade forward between the flat right shell, and cut the adductor muscle where
it joins the right shell. When the muscle has been incised, the top shell will budge.
Now let's place the oyster on a flat surface, and shuck it.
Use a twisting motion to gently pry the shells slightly apart.
Move the blade along the flat shell, and cut the adductor muscle. Be sure to keep the blade
pressed up against the inner top surface of the right shell. Otherwise, you'll risk cutting the oyster meat itself.
Now you can gently pry the top shell away from the bottom shell with the knife blade.
Pull the right shell completely off. Notice the position of the adductor muscle scar on
the inside of the right shell.
Let's identify the different organs of the oyster. The first tissue we can see is the mantle.
The mantle produces the shell and covers the internal organs.
It's made of two fleshy folds of tissues always in contact with the shells, but not attached to them.
Then, at the posterior region of the oyster, we can identify a large organ
called the adductor muscle. It's made of two parts, one large and peachy, and the other
smaller and whiteish. The adductor muscle functions to close the oyster shell.
Close to the adductor muscle, we can observe the pericardial cavity.
This cavity is filled with blood called hemolymph, and contains the heart.
Let's dissect the membrane, so we can observe the heart of the animal beating.
To collect the hemolymph and observe the blood cells, you will need a 1 mL syringe, and a
22 gauge needle.
For educational purposes, we are going to collect the hemolymph directly by punching a hole
into the pericardial cavity.
We can then observe the hemocytes using a microscope.
This short video shows you how an oyster's hemocytes phagocytocize plastic beads added
to the preparation.
These cells play an important role in oyster defense.
Let's continue describing oyster anatomy.
Below the mantle we can observe the gills.
The gills are the largest organ in the oyster's body, and consist of 4 folds of tissue.
Along with the mantle, it is the chief organ of respiration. They create water currents,
collect and sort food particles, and move food particles to the labial palps for further sorting.
they also serve to separate masses of eggs released from the ovary during spawning into
individual ova for efficient fertilization.
Close to the gill, we can observe the labial palps.
They consist of two pairs of large, soft flabs that have a roughly triangular shape.
These specialized organs are known to control the total amount of food ingested, but also sort food
before ingestion.
Unwanted material are rejected as pseudofeces. The mouth is located between the palps.
This area corresponds to the visceral mass, including the stomach.
At the end of the digestive tract at the posterior side of the animal, we can observe the rectum,
along the adductor muscle, and at the extremity, the anus.
In order to determine if the oysters are infected with the parasite Perkinsus marinus,
we will collect and incubate pieces of tissue in specific culture media called
FTM.
Let's collect a small piece of mantle, close to the labial palps.
This area is particularly important, because pseudofeces containing pathogen cells accumulate
there before being rejected in the environment. Perkinsus cells use this advantage
to penetrate oyster tissue.
The small piece is then placed in the tube containing FTM.
Perkinsus cells can also accumulate at the end of the rectum, so let's dissect a little piece
as well.
Perkinsus marinus needs lipids to enlarge.
To avoid the proliferation of bacteria and fungus, we will add antibiotics and
antifungus to the medium.
Tubes will then be stored for one week in the dark at room temperature.
To conclude on health diagnostic,
we will realize a cross section
of the animal.
After sectioning the adductor muscle and removing the oyster from its shell, we will use a scalpel
to cut a fine slide of the digestive gland.
Let's make sure we also include the mantle and gills.
Now we can take the whole section and place it into a histology cassette, that will be placed in
formalin to be fixed,
then alcohol, before being embedded in paraffin, and cut into very fine sections, for further
microscopic observation.
This concludes our oyster dissection and health diagnostic.